<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An hundred heauenly thoughts And resolutions, tending to draw the minde from euill to good. Written by W. S. preacher of Gods worde in S. Iohns of Mathermarket in Norwich.</title>
            <author>Stinnet, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1616</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 75 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 87 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11261</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21527</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112134</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847392</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847392</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12425</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11261)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12425)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1583:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An hundred heauenly thoughts And resolutions, tending to draw the minde from euill to good. Written by W. S. preacher of Gods worde in S. Iohns of Mathermarket in Norwich.</title>
                  <author>Stinnet, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 165 [i.e. 161], [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By G. Eld, and are to be sould by C. W[right],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1616.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>W. S. = William Stinnet.</note>
                  <note>Publisher's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Pages 156-61 misnumbered 160-65.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Good and evil --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12425:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12425:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12425:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12425:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12425:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12425:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN HVNDRED Heauenly Thoughts. AND RESOLVTIONS, tending to draw the minde from EVILL to GOOD.</p>
            <p>Written by <hi>W. S.</hi> PREACHER of GODS Worde in S. <hi>Iohns</hi> of Mathermarket in <hi>Norwich.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>PSAL. 1.2.</bibl>
               <p>Bleſſed is the man that Meditates in Gods Lawe, day and night.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>PRO. 14 22.</bibl>
               <p>Doe they not erre that deuiſe Euill? but mercy and truth ſhall be to them that deuiſe good.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed at London by <hi>G. Eld,</hi> and are to be ſould by C. W. 1616.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:12425:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12425:4"/>
            <head>To the Right Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull and my moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected friend M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>s. Anne Corbet (wife to tha vertuous and godly Gentleman M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. THOMAS CORBET of Sprowſton) a very wiſe godly and heauenly Gentlewoman, <hi>W.S.</hi> wiſheth all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>RIG<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>T WORSHIPFVLL.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am ſo tyed vnto you by your many fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours,
<pb facs="tcp:12425:5"/> as I profeſſe I know not how to carry my ſelfe in thankſgiuing to you. I haue heere ſome few thoughts or Meditations which may doe ſome good, I dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate them to your Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in way of thankes for your fauours. If you aske me for what vſe they be of, I anſwere they are for this vſe, to ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then vs against the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, to draw our minds
<pb facs="tcp:12425:5"/> from foule ſinnes, to ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enate our minde from this preſent world which is euill; to teach vs to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our liues well, and to lead vs foreward to the Kingdome of Heauen. Theſe thinges, whiles many others let their thoughts run a thouſand waies amiſse, I haue min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and if they ſhall be read with the minde they were written, and taken on the right hand.
<pb facs="tcp:12425:6"/> They ſhall I trust not want their due effect, and good acceptance: I know they bee not excellent, and yet I know they be not worſt. Your Worthines indeed (whom I haue oft admired) deſerues farre better: yet I pray you accept theſe, and God I truſt in time will inable mee to giue a further teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of my loue. So the Lord of glory keep
<pb facs="tcp:12425:6"/> you and all yours:</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From my Study in S. <hi>Iohns</hi> of Mather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>market in Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich, <date>this 26. of Iuly. 1616.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Worſhips in the beſt bond that may be. <hi>W. S.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:12425:7"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <l>Leaue thou the worſt,</l>
            <l>and take the beſt:</l>
            <l>Ile thanke thee then</l>
            <l>and wiſh thee bleſt.</l>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:12425:7"/>
            <head>AN HVNDRED Heauenly Thoughts, and Reſolutions, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to drawe the mind from Euill to Good.</head>
            <div n="1" type="meditation">
               <head>1.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> WORTHY thing it is to haue a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy name, for it is the principall ornament wee haue, and the faireſt flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in our Garden: I had rather haue a face disfi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gured, a houſe ruinous,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:12425:8"/> a garment tattered, and to be in any baſe conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on then to looſe my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation. Me thinkes it is like a well arayed ground or a pleaſant place more then in any other deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in. <hi>Therefore I vow, I will ſo rule my liberties, and ſo temper my vaine affection, as rude ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity ſhall haue no place to diſgrace me. Let Crowes then keepe their black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and bee contented, to feede on Carrion. I will Swan-like keepe my white<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and delight my ſelfe in the guilded ſtreames
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:12425:8"/> of goodneſſe. It is true, my weakenes is not fit for any great worthines, yet ſuch as I reſolue to vphold my ſelfe from wickedneſſe, a ſmall fire is eaſily main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, but once extinct, is not eaſily kindled.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="meditation">
               <head>2</head>
               <p>IF I ſee a man of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly carriage, and noble and wiſe behauiour, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſting a moſt vertuous mind in all his actions, I will long and holily ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:12425:9"/> him, as deſirous to get ſome taſt-pleaſing fruite of ſo fayre a tree. <hi>But if on the contrary, I ſee him of an ill fauoured diſpoſition, I will either round him in the eare with a wholſome admonition: or elſe my countenance ſhall deliuer to him in ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion, that I miſlike his wretched conuerſation.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="meditation">
               <head>3</head>
               <p>IT is a peuiſh imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, ouer bitterly to glaunce at others re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:12425:9"/> and with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logues or without pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logues, to let fly at them ſuch words as may caſt a great miſt ouer their glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: And yet this I haue often marked, that ſome liberall tongues there be, can as eaſily trauill ouer Mountaines as Mole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hills, and exerciſe the freedome of their Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, as well in a Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as a lowly ſubiect. Hence many worthy gueſts bidden to mens banquets, are ouer-preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with theſe ouer-flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtories, and to them
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:12425:10"/> cheerefulnes becomes te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſnes, and good enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynment is tourned to diſcourteſie. But alaſſe, this either argues pride, thinking to build vp their owne worthines by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers worthleſſenes: or elſe barrennes of Braine that can ſtumble on no better ſubiect, or elſe ſtore of paſſion with which they are violent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tranſported. <hi>O Lord teach me to gather fruits of Wiſedome out of theſe occaſions, and when I heare others to ſpeake bitter, I may exerciſe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:12425:10"/> my ſelfe to ſpeake better, that who ſo markes my words proceeding from me, may know my tongue a quicke meſſenger of grace, and perceiue that ſtore of Heauenly Thoughts haue Lordſhip in me.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="meditation">
               <head>4</head>
               <p>IT is an ordinary thinge among the Vulger to nouriſh vp themſelues with ouer-much hope, &amp; though they be conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with peſtilent paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſo that they be full
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:12425:11"/> of raſh enmitie, plentifull in impatient ſorrowes, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundant in idle workes, ſwelling in haughtines of heart, and deepely bemired in the baſe trade of ordinary worldlinges. Yet they thinke that of God they may be greatly fauoured: But as a child, whoſe wit farre ouergoes his age, is quickly inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted by death. So theſe ouer-ſtreching hopes quickely meete with an vnhappy repulſe. The Spider buildes and is ſafe vntill the trimmers bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome come, then ſoden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:12425:11"/> ſhe is diſplaced, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſed, diſpatcht: Lo ſuch is the vncertaine hope of the popular ſort who ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſuſpect themſelues til they be paſt themſelues. <hi>But I will build my hopes on better ſtaies and will not be ſo baſe as to make vncertainty the baſe or pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of my ſafety.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="meditation">
               <head>5</head>
               <p>VErtues skin is ſo full of braue beauty, that it ſcornes to lodge with foule impiety: it yeelds
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:12425:12"/> no acquaintance to ſin, but vnfriendly: no enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment but vnkindly; but vices like thornes can hugge togither, and loue ſo deerely, that if you handle them to make a ſeparatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they wil ſcarce ſpare your blood. Would a man thinke that faſt &amp; looſe could loue, lie, and lincke togither, they be ſo contrary, and yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, this is to be found, ſome faſt for outward thinges, looſe for inward, worldlings, and yet wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings: ſome noted and ſtedfaſt miſers, yet looſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:12425:12"/> and vnſtedfaſt miſtreſſes. <hi>But as for mee, I will ſo bee faſt as the poore ſhall vntie mee: And I will not bee ſo looſe, as the world ſhall ſhame me.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="meditation">
               <head>6</head>
               <p>SOme veſſells may laſt long, but yet at length will leake. And we know veſſells of glaſſe, though wel tempered, yet cannot long indure. Lo thus I
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:12425:13"/> haue deemed of wordly friends: If ſomwhat firme, yet not euer, for being but brittle glaſſe, they quickly breake. <hi>Then this ſhall be my renewed skill to wrap vp my matters in ſecrecie, ſince to hould out, or rather to hould in, man is of ſo ſmall ability.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="meditation">
               <head>7</head>
               <p>I ſee that many golden houres are ſpent in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting games, and manie dainty dayes in greedy getting gaines, but
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:12425:13"/> though it happen that ſome games be gaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and gaines to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers gameſome. <hi>Yet will I not encounter with ſuch ſtrange aduentures: But mine eyes, mine eares, my tongue my head ſhall ſerue for a better inquiry. For I haue alwaies deemed it miſerable to bee a man of mirth, or a man of ritches, and not to be (which paſſeth both theſe), a man of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="meditation">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:12425:14"/>
               <head>8</head>
               <p>THe aged, thinking themſelues of ſome worthines, for their long and learned experience, haue learne to diſpiſe the yong. <hi>Young folke</hi> (ſay they) <hi>thinke old folkes fooles, but old folkes know that young folkes be fooles.</hi> Contrariwiſe, young men thinking ſuch weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe not fit for worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſay, <hi>Old folkes are
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:12425:14"/> froward, but young folkes are toward.</hi> As for mee, I am neither young nor old, yet age I will reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, without contempt of youth: youth I wil loue without diſgraceing age. Age is heauy &amp; weighes down the fraile and fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ballance, but liftes vp the noble and ſpiritual part. And youth is quick and liuely, and though oft foyld with vaine and foule fancies, yet oft re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleniſhed with vertuous delights. <hi>Giue mee then an old man ſpirituall, and a young man vertuous,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:12425:15"/> and both ſhall goe for currant.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="meditation">
               <head>9</head>
               <p>We vſe to ſay that fleſh is weake: and ſo it is, how then preuailes it ſo much with men? ſurely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe men are not men, for if we be men the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable part of our ſoule is to haue ſouereigne and abſolute command, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt which if any ſenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all motions ariſe, we are to yeeld al our ſound for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:12425:15"/> to the ouerthrowing of ſo vnnaturall a rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: <hi>I will therefore take courage a freſh, and ſince I am to deale againſt ſo weake an Aduerſary that in it ſelfe is nothing but weakeneſſe, I will reſolue to reſiſt it, and what right reaſon doth direct, by Gods helpe Ile perfect.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="meditation">
               <head>10</head>
               <p>I Haue lyued this thirty yeares, and euery yeare hath 365. dayes &amp; euery
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:12425:16"/> day 24. houres ſo that one yeare hath 8760. houres, but 30. yeares, the age to which I haue attained, hath 262800. houres, now in theſe many hours, good Lord how oft haue I thought amiſſe, and if the houres amount to ſo big a ſumme, who can count my thoughts. And if to my thoughts I could adde my vnſauery and idle words, and then to theſe my omitting du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and committing ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, might I not be aſhamed, <hi>O Lord for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue thy poore Seruant
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:12425:16"/> his innumerable ſinnes, and teach me ſo to num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber my dayes, as I may apply my heart to wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="meditation">
               <head>11</head>
               <p>IT is both Godly and neceſſary, betimes to fit for death: Godly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God hath charged, that the ignorance of our diſſolution ſhould moue vs to preparation, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, ſends to vs diuers meſſengers to giue vs warning, for dulled ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:12425:17"/> weakned ioynts, gri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping griefes, and aged wrinckles, what are they but meſſengers of God to prepare vs for death. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, neceſſary, for there be two errors which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not after commiſſion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue correction: the one about marriage, the other about death: Hee then that will dye well, muſt prepare well. <hi>Oh then I will account thoſe bleſſed ſoules that thinke of theſe things, and thoſe fooliſh and vnhappy which cannot abide to heare of death. And who ſo by
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:12425:17"/> mirth or promotion would ſtop me from this prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I account him as an Hoſt ſtaying his drunken gueſt till night come, who riding then in darke, ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and breakes his necke.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="meditation">
               <head>12</head>
               <p>TO purchaſe houſes, men imploy their deepeſt wits, omitting nothing that cunning can inuent or power miniſter: for a credit they ſay it is to be an owner. <hi>But by Gods grace I will die in the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:12425:18"/> ſtreetes, before I will bee purchaſer or owner of ſome houſes. The Pallace of Pride, the ſlaughter-houſe of cruelty, the filthy ſtewes of vncleannes, the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of oppreſsion: I will e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer loath, neuer loue, nor euer by them liue.</hi> And yet in the moyſt &amp; fickle im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of my eye-ſight, behold many perſons to be Lords of ſuch, and ſo loue their houſes, as they carry them about in their hearts.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="meditation">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:12425:18"/>
               <head>13</head>
               <p>I Haue ſeene many, whom, no outward cheriſhing could ſalue the ſores of their mind; their reaſon darkened with ſorrow, their hearts greatly groning, teares haue run down their eyes &amp; their tongues haue vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred many doleful notes, their countenances trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, ſometime ſo ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, that they haue beene dangerouſly ſicke,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:12425:19"/> a ſpectacle of miſery. But why was this? ſurely God had ecclipſed his fauour and loue for ſhining on them. <hi>O Lord I will deſire aboue all things to haue thy loue, and feare nothing but to miſſe the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="meditation">
               <head>14</head>
               <p>PEace is worth ſeeking at all times, but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when the enemy is valourous, and men bee not of number to keepe the field againſt his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:12425:19"/> yea it is then worth hauing though it were with loſſe: much more to bee deſired when it may be had with reaſonable and honorable conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. O my Soule! God is Almighty in power, and thou art weake: wilt thou be proud and ſtubbornly ſtout againſt him? canſt thou match his might? Oh no. <hi>I will then value his valour, and get with loſſe his fauour, yet I ſhall not looſe ſince the forgiuer is as quicke as the deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: the forgoing of my holds in luſts may anno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:12425:20"/> but not ſo much as his deare loue will ioy me.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="meditation">
               <head>15</head>
               <p>I Haue had friends that I haue thought of value but they haue ſhaken me off either through their their vnperfectnes, or my vnworthines: <hi>I wil there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore loue the Lord aboue, with all the powers of my mind, whoſe perfect friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip no vnworthines in me nor vnperfectnes in him can once diſſolue, for whom
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:12425:20"/> that he loues once he loues euer.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="meditation">
               <head>16</head>
               <p>A Man in ill compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny is like a pretiou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pearle fallen into the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie grownd, the which the longer it lies the dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſtill it ſinkes into it. I haue pittied the caſe of ſome, that (hauing beene of honeſt diſpoſion) haue fallen into ſuch muddy mire, and ſo haue loſt their louely qualities.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:12425:21"/> 
                  <hi>But I wil rather retire into ſome dwelling ſolitary, then infect my ſoule with ſuch foule company.</hi> A chaſt Dame if once you enter into termes of affection with her ſhee is gone, and from you flyes, as the haſty Hare from the ſwift greedy Grayhound: <hi>So will I flye from i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, and greatly diſdaine to endanger my pretious graces, amongst their dir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Impieties.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="meditation">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:12425:21"/>
               <head>17</head>
               <p>I Haue often thought in the mid'ſt of Agonies, I ſhould haue bin thurſt out of my earthly habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that the weake houſe of my body would haue ſuffered an vtter o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow: And heerein ſurely I haue beene like to a Horſe, deſirous to run and miſerably ſpur'd, but ſo ſhort rayn'd by his Maiſter, as hee cannot ſtir forward: But I know
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:12425:22"/> before long the Raynes will be looſed and I ſhall bee ſo galled as I muſt runne. I will not bee ſo Horſhiſh, as to galloppe I know not whither; But ſithence my houſe is like to come to ruin, <hi>I will make preparation for a more firme dwelling, leaſt ſuddenly beeing caſt out of houſe and harbour, I bee compelled to take vp a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Lodging.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="meditation">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:12425:22"/>
               <head>18</head>
               <p>THe Lord imploying vs in dangerous en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſes, the more our vertue is tryed, yea the more pure wee grow. <hi>I will learne therefore to like and not miſlike, to loue and not to loath his ſharpeſt dealings; For while many things might ſeeme to ouer-throw vs, they ſet vs vp vppon the height of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="meditation">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:12425:23"/>
               <head>19</head>
               <p>IF any take a ſpightfull griefe at me, and would force me with ouer-vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment iniuries to breake peace, and to vtter forth the violent paſſion of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge. <hi>I will ſhew forth no other but the fruits of a gentle nature, and I will be ſo farre from bringing forth that which deſperate reuenge can imagine, that their mallice ſhall ſooner ceaſe then my vnchanged patience.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="meditation">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:12425:23"/>
               <head>20</head>
               <p>IT is no vulgar thing among the vulgar people to ſhoote their prayſes and commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions at randome, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they will ſweetly ſpeake and plentifully prayſe men of great wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe: Anon they will not ſticke to giue exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue commendations to the vileſt varlets. <hi>I will not care therefore what ſuch wether-cockes tell of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:12425:24"/> me: For I count it a great happineſſe onely to be pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of them that are moſt prayſe-worthy-</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="meditation">
               <head>21</head>
               <p>MAny thinke to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue the guifts of Heauen, and yet ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue at Gods hands a reſolute refuſall, which will bee more wofull and vnwelcome to them then a bitter deniall to an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected ſuiter: And no maruaile, for it is rather
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:12425:24"/> credit then grace that leads moſt men to mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Heauen. And when the ſpur of honour cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, they willingly reſt in their carnall delights, and follow the gentle currant of them: But now the moſt holy God hath ſuch vile men in eternall hatefulneſſe, and for ſuch carriage, there ſhall bee neither grace nor fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rableneſſe. <hi>So then I will labour that in me euery thing may bee Godly and full of ſyncerity, and ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly I vow, that neither credit nor fauour, ſhall
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:12425:25"/> make mee to ſlubber ouer duty.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="meditation">
               <head>22</head>
               <p>NO cloſe Arbour the Branches of which are ſo louingly enterla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced one within the other can reſiſt the ſtrong vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of Gods eye-ſight, nor cloſeſt roomes which vnchaſt Dames count Chambers of delight, are deſtitute of Gods hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable preſence. Why then braue Knights and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:12425:25"/> faire Ladies, and all my louely brethren &amp; Siſters, let vs rather dye then ſpot our ſelues with ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret filthines. Let vs mark a diligent and nimble dogge can finde a ſcent, which we thinke impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and when God can make ſuch a Creature to finde out ſuch a thing, ſhall not hee bee able to finde out our wickednes, though wee bee in our Dennes? <hi>Hence then I wil account it extreame folly any longer to impriſon ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="meditation">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:12425:26"/>
               <head>23</head>
               <p>AN ambitious man ſtriues to bring o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers vertuous patience vnder him, and thinkes his maiſter-hood nothing without doing iniury to men: <hi>But I dare not bee a man of ſuch excellency, leaſt God ſhould aduance me to</hi> Hamans <hi>dignity.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="meditation">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:12425:26"/>
               <head>24</head>
               <p>I Haue thought it to bee no great matter to draw many euill men to many inconueniences; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially if a man would follow them with a watch full ſeruice: for euery pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent occaſion will catch their ſenſes, and their ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are maiſters of their ſilly minds, ſo that onely reuerence them: and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light them: and with that bridle and ſaddle you ſhal
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:12425:27"/> well ride them. <hi>But as for me I am determined neuer to bee carried with ſuch an eager &amp; impatient delight of any thing, as the nimble wits of the world ſhall with their lewd inticements draw me to ſin.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="meditation">
               <head>25</head>
               <p>IT is no vnuſuall thing to make hard-wreſted conſtructions of words oft proceeding from the kindeſt natures, which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended as true, eſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:12425:27"/> loue and eclipſes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection from ſhining any longer. <hi>But I haue often thought and will doe ſtill, that the conſtruction of mens ſpeeches might bee beſt made by the Grammer-rules of affection.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="meditation">
               <head>26</head>
               <p>I Find that to a heart fully reſolute to preach the trueth, hatefull perſons and ignorant aſſes, to whom Counſell is tedious and reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:12425:28"/> loathſome (both in word and deede worke much annoyance, an eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent token of an ignorant and ſhallow mind. Shal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Brookes murmur, moſt deepe ſilent ſlide a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way: and I haue heard Pies chattering, when better Birds haue held their peace. <hi>Mine eare then ſhall ſuch vp kind Counſells and wholſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions, which true lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing teachers ſcatter before me. And I will bee ſo far from reproching them, that my kindeſt courteſie ſhall be imployed for them.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="meditation">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:12425:28"/>
               <head>27</head>
               <p>MAny men thinke on nothing but their ſports, ſeeke nothing but their ſports. To their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights their attendance is directed, and to their pleaſures the beſt fruits they can gather are brought. And ſurely once I thought theſe men in the higheſt bliſſe-ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. But experience grounded on feeling hath taught me a better leſſon,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:12425:29"/> and hath learned mee that the wickeds ſingings muſt be cloſed vp with hearty gronings. <hi>I will bleſse the Lord that hath vouchſafed to mee a better happines, and that hath lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued me ſo, as to bring me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the ſweet company of his beloued Saints: I ſay ſweet indeed, which I will not forſake for the worlds faire delights: for God is their ſaying, and God is their ſinging, and God is the Load-starre of their life, the bleſsing of their eyes, the ſweetneſse of their heart. Lord let mee
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:12425:29"/> liue and dye in this ſweet and heauenly ſociety.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="meditation">
               <head>29</head>
               <p>SOme I haue beheld very famous and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for goodneſſe, but ſince finding godlines ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry tedious, &amp; being dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tired with the length of the vnco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable labour of it, they haue diſcarded it, giuing themſelues to outragious licentiouſnes in which they ſo fleſh themſelues, as I thinke
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:12425:30"/> they meane not to ſtop their race till they come to a head-long ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw. Thus like ſome Mornings, they haue made guilden ſhewes of good meanings; but after clouds haue riſen pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring out water and blac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ouer all the face of Heauen. <hi>But I am reſolued to put forth my hand to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry moſt painefull Office, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then to bee diſſeuered from the practiſſe of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="meditation">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:12425:30"/>
               <head>29</head>
               <p>MEn may maruaile, why ſo fraile and weake a creature as man, ſhould yet ſo harden and ſtiffen himſelfe in ſinne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, as he will not bee reclaymed: But is it not becauſe his power is forgotten? his Soueraigne Lordſhip ouer al the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures not carefully conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered? For if theſe were currantly conceiued, the valianteſt of men would
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:12425:31"/> finde inward diſmayed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and bee deepely caſt downe for feare of helliſh darkeneſſe. The Marriners ſee when the Heauens fauour; the Sea fauours alſo, and they may be ſafe then and lye calmely: but if the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen frowne, and the windes begin to ſpeake loud, and as in a tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Kingdome to think themſelues fitteſt inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of commandment, then the ſea will ſtorme alſo: and the ſtouteſt of them all waxe agaſt and aſtoniſhed. <hi>I will there
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:12425:31"/> fore keepe in a cleere Hauen and ſeeke the fauour of the higheſt: and then no inferiour Creature will ſhew it ſelfe way-ward to mee.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="meditation">
               <head>30</head>
               <p>WEe count it a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable condition to bee at Sea, in ſuch a boyſtrous ſtorme as the ſhippe wherein wee are hath neither power to ſtaye, nor way to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape: but being carried
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:12425:32"/> with the Tirrany of the winde, and the treaſon of the ſea, with vnreſiſtable violence fals to deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But O how miſerable is it then to bee toſſed and tottered with the outragious furie of ſinne and Sathan, when men ſhall haue nothing in them but deſpaire of ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and an expectation of a loathſome end? This is a miſery that goes beyond the degrees of comfort. <hi>I will therefore flye vppon my ſinnes, whiles I haue time to maiſter them, and I will leaue none of them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:12425:32"/> leaſt they ſhould thus annoy me.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="meditation">
               <head>31</head>
               <p>AS it is in a ſtorme at the ſea, that in it wee may ſee the diuers man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of minds in diſtreſſe, ſome ſitting weeping and wailing, till the ſea ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them, ſome one more able to abide death then the feare of death, cuts his owne throat to preuent drowning, ſome praye, ſome curſe, as
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:12425:33"/> if the Heauens could not be more angry then they were: ſo in the ſtorme of reproofe, ſome weepe, ſome pray, ſome fret, and ſome one or other cuts his owne throat, and workes vnexpected miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe. O the forcible power of the word that hath ſuch ſtrange effects: <hi>I wil euermore admire thee, and in admiring thee loue thee.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="meditation">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:12425:33"/>
               <head>32</head>
               <p>I Haue thought often, O that I could ſerue God as I wiſh. <hi>But ſince I cannot doe as I would, I wil ſtill goe on and content my ſelfe with that meaſure of grace my fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>her hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed vppon me.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="meditation">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:12425:34"/>
               <head>33</head>
               <p>GOod men and ſuch as be of a moſt ſweet carriage and faire demea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, are often vniuſtly ſubiected to out-ragious wrongs, ill ſpeeches, rude welcomes, hard farewels be their kindeſt comforts from ill diſpoſed perſons, when as to the wicked like themſelues their hearts can tumble with ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much kindneſſe: O wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched man thus to lay the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:12425:34"/> faireſt complexion on the filthieſt fauour, and to ſet forth both in ſelf-ſluttiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: Me thinkes a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſparke of holy indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation ariſes in me while I thinke of it. No excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſpirits will doe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ſuch wrong: But ſince it hath pleaſed the higheſt power to throw good men to ſuch eſtate: <hi>I will giue paſſage to my thoughts and reſt content, knowing that though I bee a comberſome Gueſt among men, yet of God I ſhall haue ſweet refreſhing.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="meditation">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:12425:35"/>
               <head>34</head>
               <p>MAn is ſo fond as hee deſires thinges both vnlawfull and vnpoſſible<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but alas, poore wretch in ſo deſiring hee deſires pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing, for vnlawfull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires are ſurely puniſhed after the effect of inioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and impoſſible deſires are puniſhed in the deſire it ſelfe. <hi>I will not then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire any thinge, but I will waigh by Wiſdome and Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue whether it be lawful and poſſible.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="meditation">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:12425:35"/>
               <head>35</head>
               <p>DIuers young men of the braueſt minde, ledde with the blindnes of luſt and rage, neuer linne till they haue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed ſome notable miſchiefe, thinking them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues the onely men of moſt approued good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but when they haue hurt guiltleſſe perſons, and feele the ſmart of puniſhment. O the cowardiſe of a guilty
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:12425:36"/> conſcience! angry threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings and light hurts to theſe ſtrong hearts are grieuous wounds, and ſo ſtrange as they faint and know not how to beare them. <hi>So then, a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſhall bee to mee a Caſtle, out of which I will not ſtep ſo much as a haires bredth.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="meditation">
               <head>36</head>
               <p>MAny are maiſters of lands that are not maiſters of themſelues,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:12425:36"/> who though great ſhewes are made to blinde the world, yet haue no other thoughts then come of vnquiet ſenſes. Heere poyſonous heats of affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions torments them, there ſtrange gueſts in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uade their ſoules, fond and foule deſires haue ſtrength to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quer them. A wofull thing to inioy other things, but not to inioy a mans ſelfe. <hi>But I will endeauour that no ſpotted thoughts ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer mee my life to ſtaine, leaſt I fall to outragious follies.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="meditation">
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:12425:37"/>
               <head>37</head>
               <p>VVHen I conſider mans meanenes, I wonder God did not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine to lay any treaſure with him, where they are ſtayned with ſo many imperfections. But this is the will of our excellent Creator, who (whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer wee deeme) will hide rare guifts vnder ſuch ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then veſſells. <hi>Oh therefore I will giue thankes to God that ſettes a Crowne on my baſe eſtate, and vouchſafes
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:12425:37"/> to deſcend to my poore mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, meaning by his diuine hand to imbrace me, and from my baſenes to turne me vnto high preferment.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="meditation">
               <head>38</head>
               <p>SOme haue intangled themſelues ſo in folly, that they be tyed faſt with the bonds of neceſſity: but hee that ſuffers him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to bee ſurprized by neceſſity, doth no more any thing freely his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels is and actions ſauour
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:12425:38"/> of a troubled iudgement. <hi>I vow then to keepe my ſelfe from folly, that I may thinke and doe at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="meditation">
               <head>39</head>
               <p>TO doe well among men of honour is ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie and ordinary, but not to ſuffer himſelfe to bee tranſported with the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions of the time, nor to followe the violent paſſions of a multitude, but to deſire the good, to dare vndertake it, and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:12425:38"/> to effect it in a bad ſeaſon, in the which vice is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured with the recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of vertue, it is an infallible argument of a ſpirit wonderfully diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by nature to all good &amp; commendable things. <hi>I purpoſe therefore by Gods grace in the midſt of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption to haue vertue for my portion.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="meditation">
               <head>40</head>
               <p>OF great friends are made greateſt enemies
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:12425:39"/> hatred ſo followes and accompanies friendſhip, <note place="margin">Plutarch.</note> 
                  <hi>Chilon</hi> tolde him that vaunted hee had no e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies that hee ſhould alſo haue no friendes. <hi>I will then ſo vſe my friends, as I looke they ſhould bee mine enemies, and onely my God ſhall bee my ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt hold who in the day of trouble knowes them that truſt in him.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="meditation">
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:12425:39"/>
               <head>41</head>
               <p>IT is hard to repaire and recompence the iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries done to faith and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation. <hi>Famae et fidei damna maiorae ſunt, quam quae aeſtimari queant.</hi> The loſſes of our fame and faith be greater then can be deemed. <hi>I will be wary then how I runne on ſuch rockes as giues mee ſuch knockes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="meditation">
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:12425:40"/>
               <head>42</head>
               <p>CHriſtianity I haue oft re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled to a ſchoole in which are golden bookes, and ſeuere, yet fruitfull teachers. But as inother ſchooles it fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently falls out, ſo in this: For as I haue ſeene trimme bookes dight in veluet, and decked with golden leaues, much pleaſe the vnacquainted ſight of ſilly boyes, vntill the Rod began to play his part, then they would faine be gon: ſo whilſt many fooles haue apprehended pleaſing ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects in <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſchoole, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity ſhould bee as deare to them as their emboſomed
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:12425:40"/> gueſt, but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the maiſter hath giuen ſome noyſome blowes, as ill appointed Knights they flye the field, and ſucke from thence a mortal miſlike of ſuch a life: <hi>But with good grace I ſpeak it, in this ſchoole all things are beautifull: And with a feeling declaration my tongue ſhall vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that my teachers blowes bee ſweeteſt blowes of loue.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="meditation">
               <head>43</head>
               <p>I Haue thought of thoſe that doe abuſe the Miniſters, that they doe corrupt the watch-men Oh then! when the great Captaine ſhall come the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:12425:41"/> corrupter and the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted ſhall ſmart for it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="meditation">
               <head>44</head>
               <p>I See many noble wits bende themſelues to mean ſubiects when they might bend their minds to higher thoughts: they furniſh themſelues with very faire apparrell, fine deckings they think much beautifie them: they e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect ſtately buildings, dainty deuices much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light them; huntings,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:12425:41"/> hawkings, gamings, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cings and dauncing bee onely ioyes: They giue noble entertainment to ſtrangers: ſhew franke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of minde to friends, and ſet out euery thing in moſt gorgeous man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to the dignifying of their honour. But where bee the men whoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of minde hath taken vp a well choſen courſe in vertue? where be the men that haue well trained and long exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed their minds in more excellent and heauenly contemplations, that
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:12425:42"/> haue apparelled &amp; deckt their mind with grace: A man might ſhew thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands to theſe things ſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enclyned whiles they omitte no toyle nor ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice in the other. Vnhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py men ſo to diuert their thoughts from the wayes of goodnes, and to looſe, nay to abuſe their time, I beare great honour to the names of theſe: <hi>But Lord let me be bedded in my graue, rather then wedded to ſuch iniquity as ſhould cauſe my affections to bee eſtranged from thee.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="meditation">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:12425:42"/>
               <head>45</head>
               <p>RIch men are counted the richeſt Iuels, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they bee neither well formed by nature, nor framed by education to the true exerciſe of vertue: Theſe haue the largeſt prayſes, the moſt earme intreaties, the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Titles, the moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſeruice, and the loweſt reuerence: Theſe be reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the onely bleſſed, the high Cedars, the rich Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bies the only ſhining ſuns. But
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:12425:43"/> if God haue any skill in painting out mens con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions mens markes bee taken amiſſe: for hee will tel vs ritches without ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue is nothing gratefull, and ſome that haue been acquainted with ritch mens priuate ſorrowes, will conſtantly affirme that their muddy abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance is full of carking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonies. Kings Crownes cannot help them from the cruell head-ach, nor ſhooes of gold preſerue from the painfull gout. <hi>I wil neuer therfore plunge my thoughts into ritches
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:12425:43"/> bondage, but looke after and long for my heauenly inheritage.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="meditation">
               <head>46</head>
               <p>I Maruaile much why men ſhould bee tranſ- with ſuch ouer-vehement affection, to taſt ſo gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily of the worlds vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and ſo much to let looſe the raines of their deſires to ſuch fickle mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueables. What conceit is it they build vppon? do they thinke ſuch onely fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uored
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:12425:44"/> and aduanced of God? No, the eternall ſpring of vertue teſtifies he hath ſuch men in eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall hatefulnes: doe they thinke to be honoured of men? Oh yes, with Churle and Carle and Cormo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and ſuch deformed titles. <hi>So then, I will ſeeke no better wealth then a qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et Conſcience, nor greater pleaſures then heauens ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies. Stand far then filthy Couetouſnes from me: Ile be no Carle no Kite, no Cormorant, but a liberall Chriſtian, a liberal Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an is my name, and a libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:12425:44"/> Chriſtian is my title, &amp; Chriſtianity which loues liberallity ſhall be the onely hope of my aduancement: For my names ſake I cannot loue thee, and for my ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers ſake I muſt and wil de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt thee.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="meditation">
               <head>47</head>
               <p>I Haue often thought eating, drinking, and ſtuffing the carcaſſe, a ſhrewd burden and intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable yoke; it dulls the cheerfull limbs, and hales the body to vnworthy
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:12425:45"/> ſeruitude: to long and ſtrong diſeaſes, to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing pangs, and after to vntimely deathes: it bemires the thoughts of the ſoule deepely in the trade of vncleanneſſe: it hinders the vigorous minde from feeding on higher thoughts. <hi>The e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal God forbid then that I ſhould ſo bee fettered, Let mighty beaſts be ſtalled and fatted with their dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty variety. I will take a more happy reſolution, and ſtrike ſuch faſt friendſhip with ſober moderation as my minde ſhall bee a free
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:12425:45"/> maiſter to entertaine whole armies of heauenly thoughts and my body a ready ſeruant forth-with to welcome ſuch noble gueſts. I will thinke it foule ſcorne to yeeld my ſanctified body to ſuch ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity. And I will not bee ſuch an enemy to my ſelfe, as to impriſon my ſelfe, or to defile my ſelfe with groſse impurity.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="meditation">
               <head>48</head>
               <p>SOme Vertues among foule Vices, are like
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:12425:46"/> Pearles in a dunghill. I haue knowne ſome of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding good parts, full of wittineſſe, admirable for tongue delight, indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with cleere vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings and hony-flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpeech, and almoſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery way ſo excellent, as if a man would make a diſcription of them, a man might ſet ſuch a note vppon them, as might make them very notable vnto you: yet their, exceeding worldli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe with their cloſe hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, hath altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſgraced the other
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:12425:46"/> aſſembly of their moſt commendable vertues, no otherwiſe then rag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged penurie oft ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwes a louely beauty. <hi>I will labour therefore that euery part of my life may be an ornament to me. And as I loue not a ragged ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for decency, nor a patcht payment for mony: ſo neither like I to tender a torne life to Gods diuine excellency: but bearing ſhewes in my countenance of honeſty and well minded<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. I will reſolue in all things to be blameleſſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="meditation">
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:12425:47"/>
               <head>49</head>
               <p>IF cruell and fierce beaſts did range in dangerous ſort anongſt vs, wee would carefully prouide good defences a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch miſchiefes, giuing thoſe beaſts ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny mortall and manfull wounds, how maruellous a matter is it then, that when the horrible foule Diuell, like a ramping and roaring Lyon, furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly proſecutes vs, wee imploy not our endeauors
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:12425:47"/> to his ouerthrow, but ſuffer him to faſten his clawes (moſt cruell im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of wonderfull paſſions) vpon vs. <hi>Oh thou in whom all power and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence is harboured, teach me thy truth, a ſufficient bulwarke againſt ſuch miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="50" type="meditation">
               <head>50</head>
               <p>VVHat hath man that may make him ſo lickerous of commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, his ſtout and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious heart, alas, as it is
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:12425:48"/> ſometime valiant, ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten it is ouerpreſſed with mighty paſſions of griefe and feare; his iudgement: why the deepeſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is oft miſtaken, and groſſly erres, reaſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing growne a ſeruant to paſſions: his ſharpe wit? why the beſt wits are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten troubled with vnper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwadable melancholly, yea many their wittes crackt with violent affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: his wiſdome? what need he when he hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Paragons: his braue beauty? why the ſtate of the mind is better then
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:12425:48"/> the ſtate of the body, and we know that aged wrinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kles deface faireſt faces. Laſtly his ritches or plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures? why outward de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights and fertill grounds are but halting helpes to decaying ſoules. <hi>Lo then I will count my ſelfe vile, and know my weaknes to be vnfit for any worthineſſe: and if my friends in their ſpeeches giue me any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation, I will thinke they ſpeake not ſo much of iudgement as blinded with affection.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="51" type="meditation">
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:12425:49"/>
               <head>51</head>
               <p>I Haue often ſeene a poore man inritching his cloathes, and a weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy man whoſe cloathes haue inritched him: In the former, his beſt part is inward, in the latter, his beſt outward. <hi>But tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I had rather bee in rude rayment, with an vnſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſimplicity, then to bee ſet in higheſt dignity with folly.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="52" type="meditation">
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:12425:49"/>
               <head>52</head>
               <p>IT is great indiſcretion to bandy againſt a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er inuincible and match<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, ſuch power hath GOD: the valianteſt of men that dare oppoſe him ſhall finde diſmayd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. They can no more auaile then the Emmot pull downe a Cedar: <hi>I am reſolued then to put my hand to euery painfull office that I may pleaſe my GOD, but I will neuer dare to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:12425:50"/> wickedneſſe to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoking of him.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="53" type="meditation">
               <head>53</head>
               <p>OFt haue I muſed what monſter wrought my harme in blunting if not breaking the loue of my deereſt &amp; neereſt friends: <hi>At length I found that ſuſpition and facility to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue all things, ruins friendſhip and batters the walls of the ſweeteſt and fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt affections: oh then that ſome of my friends would
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:12425:50"/> be leſſe ſuſpitious, and not ſo credulous, that my choy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſt friends might not proue ſo vnkinde and boyſtrous. It is a very ſenſible diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to be refuſed of a deere friend.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="54" type="meditation">
               <head>54</head>
               <p>MEn are more diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented to ſee them-ſelues fruſtrated of things promiſed, then of thoſe which are but ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped for: in the one there is but miſhap, &amp; they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine onely of fortune
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:12425:51"/> in the other contempt, and they challenge him that hath broken his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe. <hi>I will promiſe nought then but what I meane to performe, for I know the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of man is more ſenſible of contempt then of loſſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="55" type="meditation">
               <head>55</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THe iuſt</hi> (ſaith GOD) <hi>ſhall liue by faith.</hi> I will thinke then euery daie I riſe I haue no life, if I doe not walke all that daie by faith, doing
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:12425:51"/> nothing but that may ſeeme good in the eyes of GOD, and what I am ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſwaded pleaſes him</p>
            </div>
            <div n="56" type="meditation">
               <head>56</head>
               <p>IT was well ſaid. <hi>Kings Crownes doe not helpe them from the cruell head-ach: nor ſhooes of gold doth heale the gout.</hi> Riches auaile not in the day of wrath, but righteouſneſſe deliuers from death, this is a receiued rule. How is it then young men wax ſo
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:12425:52"/> proud of wealth and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent age ſo lofty. An a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged Gentleman of an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued goodneſſe could ſay. <hi>That this boyiſh bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery would bring one daie a perplexed minde.</hi> How ſhall wiſe men like then ſuch Gentlemen as be ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt in euery preſent hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, and make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues braue in their owne liking. Oh bee they not like a bubble blowne vp with their owne ſmall-proud breath and quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhall be broken with a greater. <hi>Had I then mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions of gold I would thinke
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:12425:52"/> that theſe outward plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures would ſmally pleaſure my ſoule:</hi> Small greatnes heere, if guilty conſcience neere. <hi>I thinke it greater greatneſſe to get the ſureſt kingdome.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="57" type="meditation">
               <head>57</head>
               <p>EXperience hath taught me, Miſeries doe oft begin when as they ſeeme to end. Haue I not known ſome diſcarded after ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny notable deſerts, which was the more notable to them becauſe they fell
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:12425:53"/> from exceſſe of fauour from a heape of ſweetes expected, to a heape of ſorrow, rejected. Haue I not knowne ſorrow creepe ſuddenly amidſt ioy, whiles friends treate of marrying, newes comes of death. <hi>I thinke then there is not any man, but may haue more harme then hee hath had good. If hony come then and the ſweeteſt pleaſures, I vowe to looke for change, and to expect, that Sorrow like a Beare is ready to giue mee a ſhrewd imbracement.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="58" type="meditation">
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:12425:53"/>
               <head>58</head>
               <p>IT is vſuall amongſt men to accuſe <hi>Nature,</hi> or elſe mens company, or to caſt their complaints on the euill times, or ſome way or other to deminiſh ſin, and to forme for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ſubſtantial excuſes. They are cunning to find pleaſing names for things which are bitter and nought. But alaſſe this is nothing. Hee that will breake with his friend ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:12425:54"/> failes to finde occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſo may wee a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, if wee will breake with GOD. <hi>I proteſt I will neuer doe ſo. No remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of others noughti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſhall delight mee to guild ouer my guiltineſſe, if it ſhould what did I elſe, but make my ſcratchings incu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable wounds.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="59" type="meditation">
               <head>59</head>
               <p>I Haue often obſerued that many mornings
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:12425:54"/> make guilden ſhewes of good meanings, and yet afterwards clowdes haue riſen powring out water and blacking ouer all the face of heauen. Surely not vnlike haue I ſeene a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the ſonnes and daughters of men. Lord what glittering ſhewes haue I beheld, whence I haue diſcied the fouleſt and blackeſt heart? What calmenes of ſea? whence ſodainly hath roſe outra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious waues: what louing company? milde mouth? hony words? when vnder all hath cloſely beene
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:12425:55"/> diſſembled a cruel minde: Lord ſhield me from ſuch vgly beaſts, whom thou wilt one day fling into the pit of helliſh darkneſſe. <hi>I know there is no danger carries with it more horror then this ſo aduerſe to thy truth. Keepe me therefore from this deſperate dau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="60" type="meditation">
               <head>60</head>
               <p>INiuries done to faith and reputation, are not eaſily repaired, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenced,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:12425:55"/> yet men through deſperate ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion do oft commit this outragious wrong: what euill ſurmiſes, ſhrewd ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitious mad meditations be in ſome? which being carried with the current of this diſpoſition, doe receiue all thinges with the hardeſt interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, condemne all men of euill, becauſe their minde hath no eye to eſpie goodneſſe? But what is there not but in hard wreſted conſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons may bee counted a blot: ſo men of incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:12425:56"/> worth may be deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. <hi>I vow to driue away ſuch beaſtly furies, and to ſcowre my head of ſuch ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, leaſt they bee an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy occaſion of ſtaining my brothers reputation.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="61" type="meditation">
               <head>61</head>
               <p>THe tongue wel tuned makes moſt pleaſant muſicke, and is to man a principall ornament: but men haue made it a very falſe Embaſſador deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring affections whereof their heart is vtterly void.
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:12425:56"/> What dolorous diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſhall you heare when heart within hath mighty delight? what mighty de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights when heart with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in makes dolorous diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe? What kindely termes tongue turneth out, when malicious mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is wrapt in ſecrecie? What mallice in mouth when kinde conceits with in? What coy and thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring ſpeeches oft deny a thing, when the heart with dumbe eloquence deſires it. And are not theſe now excellent people? The falſe Embaſſador muſt
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:12425:57"/> bee cut off for his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, ſo let the tongue of ſuch bee cut out that talke on ſuch a faſhion. <hi>Ile tune my tongue aright; if ſighes hearty ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>unds, if cheerefull be my heart, my tongue ſhall ſhew it.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="62" type="meditation">
               <head>62</head>
               <p>CHriſt was more pure then the niceſt eye can finde a ſpot in, his iudgement ſound, his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections ſpotleſſe, his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:12425:57"/> worthineſſe ſhined through the fouleſt miſts. No maruell if hee bee ſet for our example. O rare example! not to be hoped for of any other. Away from me all yee that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in horrible foulenes: I delight not in your vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſant company, your life is ruſty and ilfauored. <hi>I wil caſt mine eye to my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued Sauiour: hee was full of beauty, ſweetnes, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Conuerſation.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="63" type="meditation">
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:12425:58"/>
               <head>63</head>
               <p>THe haughty heart of man thinkes it foule ſcorne willingly to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to bee ruled by Gods teachers: they nouriſh themſelues in ouermuch vaine hope: But did they know and acknowledge their value, what heart ſo hard, and eare ſo barbarous, but would bee imployed to heare and yeeld. Would men would giue reſolute refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalls
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:12425:58"/> or happy reſolutions to heare his voyce. <hi>Ile tread the path let them now follow. Speake Lord for thy ſeruant heareth: what thou biddeſt be done I reſolue to vndertake.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="64" type="meditation">
               <head>64</head>
               <p>COnceit is much: ſome thinke ſo highly of their owne, as others can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not reach vnto them, but if they bee croſt with bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Conceits, then burſt
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:12425:59"/> they out into rage and bitterneſſe, ſuch trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome effects ſelfe-conceit breeds: Then will they lye and ſweare to get ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage: But by their leaue who ſo tells a lye and ads an oath: I count his conceits deceits, and I eſteeme him weake in witte and vile in conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. <hi>O Lord then let me not brag much of any wit I haue, leaſt while I would ſhew my ſelfe witty, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate a heart too farre poſſeſſed with folly.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="65" type="meditation">
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:12425:59"/>
               <head>65</head>
               <p>ALl men couet to bee Beſt, fayne would we ſurpaſſe one another, but the wronge courſe is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: Hard fayre, great iournies, dangerous at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, miſchiuous Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells, vnmercifull force, mortall wounds are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-gone and vnder-ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and all to bee Beſt, that is forſooth to bee ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſt: But alaſſe it is not ſo, hee that ſinnes leaſt is
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:12425:60"/> the beſt man, and he that ſinnes moſt is the worſt. <hi>Oh then, I will flye from ſinne, and I will account my ſelf excellenteſt, when from ſinne I can ſtand the far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="66" type="meditation">
               <head>66</head>
               <p>VVHen learned men come amonge rude &amp; vnskilfull ſwaines, they many times haue not ordinary courteſie from them, yea often they haue giuen vnto
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:12425:60"/> them an vnkind and ſhrewd welcome, I mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile not at it, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them and vertue there was neuer knit a faſt frendſhippe by any edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. Their witte is ſo baſe they cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the beauty and ſweetnes of a learned life: But though ſuch loue to drinke on the draffe, let my life bee ſpent among the learned breaſts: For this I know: <hi>Hee that lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the learned to liue with the ignorant may hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen on ſome wealth, but hee ſhall neuer bee wiſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="67" type="meditation">
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:12425:61"/>
               <head>67</head>
               <p>Who ſo hath gotten vertue poſſeſſes a La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of great beauty, and ſuch a beauty, as ſhewes forth the beames of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, where euer it comes. Indeed deepe ſorrowes, ſtrange wrongs, often mightily darken her excellency for a time. But as the excellent and ſwift running Sunne quickly breakes out, and kindely cheeres the ſhort and
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:12425:61"/> ſweet nibled graſſe, ſo La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy vertue quickly adorns her owner, and well a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rayes him with moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant grace. <hi>Lord giue mee vertue then rather then the exquiſiteſt dainties and daintieſt varieties, that high conceits can fancy.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="68" type="meditation">
               <head>68</head>
               <p>I Hold it a baſe thing to be ſtraitened by vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ſeruitude, a man can not then goe to behold delightfull proſpects, nor
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:12425:62"/> ſtep aſide to haue his ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull minde ſupported. Hee cannot walke to heare the cherefull and well tuned Birds, or to ſee the pretty Lambes with bleating oratorie craue the dammes comfort, limited he is, and he muſt giue attendance. But more baſe I deeme it, when Sathan ſo ſhall fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a man, that hee may not behold Gods holy Temple, where hee may haue his ſorrowfull ſoule ſolaced with Preachers breath, more ſweete then South-weſt winde,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:12425:62"/> that hee cannot heare Gods ſweete wel-tuned Birdes, nor ſee Gods Lambes deſiring milke.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="69" type="meditation">
               <head>69</head>
               <p>DEath ſtrikes to ſome a dreadfull terrour, others are not moued at his terrible counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, but by their hardines deſpiſe death. Some when hee comes giues him a cheereful wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come. The firſt is baſe and
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:12425:63"/> ſeruile, the ſecond is cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage without skill, the third is truely valiant. <hi>Lord giue mee a reſolute heart that when I ſhall bee dangerouſly ſicke I may not faint: Let mee haue courage guided with skill, and skill armed with courage, that when death ſhal caſt his ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full dart, I may giue thee my heart, and leauing this world, I may feed my mind with higher thoughts, and more excellent contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, longing to be in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, my delightfull country and my heauenly dwelling.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="70" type="meditation">
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:12425:63"/>
               <head>70</head>
               <p>HOnour oft fetches his earth where hee will grow from out of the popular ſort: ſo lowe dunghills are fetcht to faireſt fields: but whiles the poore earth is thus exalted, it gets a new qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and holds no more his former, then the child that hath leaue to play, holds the laſt part of his leſſon. <hi>Times alter natures, &amp; honors change manners:</hi>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:12425:64"/> So ſuch as haue diſdained all chamber delights, now like and entertaine them with pleaſant diſcourſing. Thoſe who would not thinke a thought, that is not weighed by wiſdome and vertue, now can che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh moſt abominable actions. <hi>O Lord though thou ſhouldſt ſet mee high yet let me know a vertuous heart will neuer yeeld to villany.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="71" type="meditation">
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:12425:64"/>
               <head>71</head>
               <p>FRiendſhip now a dayes is ſo rare, as it is to bee doubted whether it bee a thing indeede, or but a word, moſt make loue to others, and yet loue no body but them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: ſweet termes and kindeſt courteſie, things ordinarye, when yet their heartes within bee naughty. But howſoeuer their walke bee cloſe, yet often-times their
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:12425:65"/> owne feet betray them, for they themſelues vtter themſelues to be but ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. O il imployed cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie! <hi>I beare great honour to a friend that is hearty, but Lord let me loath hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie and all ſuch hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane inhumanity. I know ſome friends whoſe wordes bring forth actions, God bleſſe them, and continue them vnto me, but if euer it fall that I looſe them, I ſhall haue hearty mourning for the loſſe of their ſweet conuerſation.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="72" type="meditation">
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:12425:65"/>
               <head>72</head>
               <p>GOd is too ſtrong for my poore power to reſiſt, hee can either with cunning or with force, or rather by his cunning force diſfigure and deface me: as he gaue me a time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly birth, ſo hee can giue mee an vntimely death. <hi>O then how great ſoeuer my other buſines bee (Oh moſt mighty God) I wil moſt wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly wait on thee, though my weake body bee as a rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:12425:66"/> houſe, yet thou canſt make mee dwell in ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="73" type="meditation">
               <head>73</head>
               <p>IN my time I haue met with ſtrange and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſant changes. Oft I haue found ouer-vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment conſtancy hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſodaine Apoſtacie, and pleaſant company turn'd to be the forgers of folly. This hath made me cry out. <hi>A conſtant Louer is an admirable Creature.</hi>
                  <pb n="119" facs="tcp:12425:66"/> But though ſuch bee the times. <hi>I am reſolued to carry my ſelfe in all my demeanour, ſo conſtantly that I will indure any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity, rather then in her ſweeteſt growth to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy vertue.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="74" type="meditation">
               <head>74</head>
               <p>IF Hippocrites bee once vnmasked, fame will bee verie prodigall of ſo notable an acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent: and all will vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand what before the
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:12425:67"/> fortifier of wickedneſſe had concealed. It will make mountaines of their ſinnes, and ouer theſe the hipocrite as a toſſing and tottering ſhip on wallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing waues, ſhall mount a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loft to be ſtraight carried downe to the pit of hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh darkeneſſe. Thus ſhall they bee carried by the tirranny of fames blaſt. And the longer they liue in ſin, the more wayward will fame bee to them. <hi>Lord keep me from all cloſe diſſembling that ſuch out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious waues may neuer ſhake me.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="75" type="meditation">
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:12425:67"/>
               <head>75</head>
               <p>SOmetimes with heed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full obſeruation I haue beheld the water Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ells ſport: he hunts the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Ducke, he waites to ſpye her riſe againe, hee ſwims, he ſnuffles, hee in weedes himſelfe, and all to pleaſe his maiſter and make him ſportfulneſſe. O what a wretch is man that imitates not this Creatures dilligence! <hi>Euen with my ſtrongest de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:12425:68"/> I wiſh I may ſhew more ſedulity in ſeruing my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther heauenlily, leaſt this Creatures dilligence doe ſhamefully condemne me.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="76" type="meditation">
               <head>76</head>
               <p>MAny vile things we ſee, to which wee are carried with an ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and impatient delight which things whiles thus we diſorderly loue, wee diſguiſe our bodies and disfigure our mindes but
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:12425:68"/> then eſpecially if led with ſwiftneſſe of deſire, any thing croſſe vs. <hi>Loue croſt is a monſtrous Lyon:</hi> and like a valiant beaſt with open Iawes it teares vs. <hi>I haue ſaid in my heart then I will looke to my wayes my deſires ſhall bee to thee O Lord. Not whatſoeuer likes me ſhall bee beutifull, but what likes thee ſhall bee to me delightfull.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="77" type="meditation">
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:12425:69"/>
               <head>77</head>
               <p>THis world is ſoe far poſſeſſed with ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that nothing is ſo ſtrong can purge it of that infection. The Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of God leaue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing vnſaid which their wit can make them know, or their deepe loue to people can require of them yet nothing auailes. They vſe more cunning intreating for mens a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode in Gods holy feare,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:12425:69"/> then any greedy Hoſt can vſe to a well paying paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger. Yet cannot their prayers preuaile. Yea Gods rod deeply wounds and oft he wounds againe and rubs vs with greefes afreſh, yet ſuch is ſecurity in men, as they can no more lay it from them, then the Crow can bee perſwaded by the Swan to caſt off all his blacke feathers. <hi>But Lord let mee remember, a child that feares not the rod, will hardly proue gratious, and men that liue ſecure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and feare not God will
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:12425:70"/> bee in Hell, ere they bee aware.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="78" type="meditation">
               <head>78</head>
               <p>IT cannot be imagined how well ſome haue conned the leſſon of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crecy. They are ſo artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall, as they cannot be hunted out of their villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. They can beare ſhewes in their countenance of honeſt and well minded men and with ſeeming vertue ſatiſfie others
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:12425:70"/> when no goodneſſe is nouriſhed in their hearts. Theſe ſteale ſinne, and none muſt know it, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther muſt any fame bring it to our eares. But doe theſe perſons thinke to ſee Heauens excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies? or thus to delude and mocke GODS Holy Maieſty. <hi>Oh no, ſtolne ſinnes are ſweet if the ſtea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler could ſcape, but hee ſhall be catcht and ſo ſhall pay for his hunting.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="79" type="meditation">
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:12425:71"/>
               <head>79</head>
               <p>IT is ſtrange to ſee the vnmanlike cruelty of of mankind, for many are ſo tirannically ambitious, as they thinke their mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterhoods nothing worth, vnleſſe they doe iniury to the vertuous. Hence to holy ones are ſtired vp wronges and griefes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable. They are miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vſed, ſlandred, belyed and what not? Their tables are ſerued with bitter rootes
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:12425:71"/> and furniſhed with ſallets of wormewood: A foole and a knaue cannot take thought, whilſt an honeſt heart is full of ſorrowes. But ſure it is. <hi>A noble cauſe eaſes much a gieuous caſe.</hi> This is the Godlies gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ſolace. And though man to man bring miſery, yet comfort enough in this, if thou be free from iniquity. <hi>If I meet then with Helhownds that croſse mee, yet Ile take heed that ſight of ſin doe not alſo toſſe mee.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="80" type="meditation">
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:12425:72"/>
               <head>80</head>
               <p>YOung Gentlemen ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times are carried with ouer-vehement de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to ſee and behould the rare ſights of forraine nations: therefore they take great iournies ſtrang courſes, vnder goe often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times vnpleaſant compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies: and ſometimes get mortall wounds and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell executions. They oft goe ſo farre as they neuer returne, meeting
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:12425:72"/> with vnexpected miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs, But as for me I wel can ſay. A farre trauai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ler ſeeth much but hee that goes to Heauen makes a happy iournie. <hi>The rare ſights of this world ſhall neuer ſo pleaſe my fancie, as they ſhall draw mee from the rauiſhing delights I ſee in diuinity.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="81" type="meditation">
               <head>81</head>
               <p>SInnes committed cauſe mighty griefe to a
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:12425:73"/> holy heart: but God teaches his how to driue away the extreamity of ſorrow, and to obtaine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundant ioyfulnes: ſight of ſinne with narrow eies: humble ſubmiſſion for deadly deedes: vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment deſire for mercifull fauour, ſtrong reſolutions of future obedience make a ſweet electuary to chaſe away griefes furie. An electuary comfortable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, for ſo the ſinner e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcapes his deadly danger. <hi>Yet this I haue alwaies thought, the eſcape out of ſinns danger is comfortable,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:12425:73"/> yet to keepe quite out of it, is a heape of wiſdome.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="82" type="meditation">
               <head>82</head>
               <p>MAny men in this world haue goodly portions, which yet are vnfit for the meaneſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultations. How oft doe wee ſee wiſdomes and vertues precepts, better followed by a beggar then by ſuch as be richer, great ones often make a mocke at vertue, and many be fortunate that
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:12425:74"/> be not wiſe. But who ſo happily hath this double portion, to follow ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue as well as riches. <hi>I ſhall bleſſe my eyes with that ioyfull ſight, and ſhall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme ſuch as moſt pretious iewells.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="83" type="meditation">
               <head>83</head>
               <p>WEe ſee many rich men fairly and han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomely attired as though they were children of the Summer, they poſſeſſe faire fieldes, ride on milke
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:12425:74"/> white horſes, ſit in coa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches richly furniſhed in black and red and all va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety. Surely moſt come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſights, and ſuch as calls the ruder eye to view them. Yet the godly wiſe can ſee that many of theſe are vilely foule and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hanſome in their mindes and ſoules, in the workes of God as ſlow as ſloweſt Iades. <hi>I wil deeme of theſe, as theſe vſe to ſpeak of their horſes. A faire horſe is comely to looke on, but if he proue heauy, hee is nought for trauell.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="84" type="meditation">
               <pb n="136" facs="tcp:12425:75"/>
               <head>84</head>
               <p>TRauailers whiles they iournie, ſome-time they ſtep into delicate greenes and moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant grounds cunningly be ſet with trees able to ſhelter from a ſhower, ſometimes they walke on barren heathes, where if ſturdy ſtormes doe come, they can finde no redreſſe. Loe ſuch is the life of man now faire, now foule, now ſweet, now ſowre,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:12425:75"/> now greene, but ſtraite mirie: ſomtime full of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectation, anon turmoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with affliction. <hi>But ſince I muſt trauaile through this worlds wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. I reſolue to account my aflictions as my neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry buſineſſe yea and on good experience I ſpeake it.</hi> The Stormes of affliction ſcoures the faithfull, <hi>and happy ſhall he be indures to the end.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="85" type="meditation">
               <pb n="138" facs="tcp:12425:76"/>
               <head>85</head>
               <p>IT is a wonder to ſee, how deuoutly religious many ſeeme to be, which yet are nothing ſo. They will ſhew a moſt pure and dainty complexion (ſo that the viewer ſhall bee wonderfully miſtaken) and yet bee moſt vile in their conuerſation. Stay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thoughts and vertuous wordes ſhall yeelde you proofes of their goodnes, but in the vttermoſt euent
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:12425:76"/> of matters, all proues a rotten Carkas. <hi>My care ſhall be then that my deeds ſhall be ſutable to my words. And I will teſtifie that as I thinke and ſpeake, ſo I deſire to doe vertuouſly, for els my enemies may rightly ſay, great boaſt &amp; ſmall roſt makes a cold kitchin.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="86" type="meditation">
               <head>86</head>
               <p>VVHere Lady Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue takes vp her lodging, Dilligence waites on her with moſt
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:12425:77"/> humble ſeruice, but idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes is ſhut out of doores, ſhe dares not ſpeake, no nor looke (as from her mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable ſelfe) vnto her hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly highnes: for her ſteps are too ſlowe to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low vertues traine, and therefore ſhee denies her ſeruice. <hi>I reſolue then to be full of ſedulity, that I may keep Lady vertue company. I will not bee like ſuch Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewomen that marre their complexions, and conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with lying long in bed, when as they might haue made a handkercher by that time they riſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="87" type="meditation">
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:12425:77"/>
               <head>87</head>
               <p>TO ſet out ſtrifes is a matter to monſtrous for my capacity: I haue earneſtly beſought ſome for peace when they haue burſt out to fury and ſhewne far more ſtirring motions to iniqu ty. But are not theſe worſe then flyes &amp; more abſurd then Ants. The flyes liue toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in ſwarmes, and the Ants liue quietly in heaps but men can hardly make
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:12425:78"/> a company to liue in qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et. <hi>But O Lord let me inioy peaceablenes, while others are ouercome with ſtrifes tediouſnes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="88" type="meditation">
               <head>88</head>
               <p>IF we ſee faire and beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull perſons, we are oft vehemently carried with ſhews of affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to them: wee then take liberty to looſe the raines to our ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes delights: and our rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon now ſeruile to paſſion accepts no ſatisfaction without inioying. <hi>But O how oft haue I beene taught
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:12425:78"/> that poyſoned drinke may be in a golden cup. When I ſee then a woman of beauty, Ile watch if I can ſpy any vertue: If I deſcry none, Ile not care a ſtraw for her company.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="89" type="meditation">
               <head>89</head>
               <p>A Bleſſed man he is that hath ſuch qualities as he is beloued in all good companies, &amp; whoſe ſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety draws to godlines: but curſed are thoſe whoſe foule courſes cary men to wickednes. To which not onely nature bends them
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:12425:79"/> but the baſe bringing vp they receiue at their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents hands confirmes them. <hi>But if hee that ſets a a traueller out of his way commits villany, ſo theſe drawing out of the way of heauen, ſhall ſmart for ſuch iniquity.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="90" type="meditation">
               <head>90</head>
               <p>THe children of God me thinkes are full of beauty: I finde in them moſt louely ſweetneſſe. Lambes they bee, and
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:12425:79"/> therefore gentle, Doues they bee, and therefore ſimple. The wicked mee thinkes are full of defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity: I finde in them moſt loathſome bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Dogges they bee, and therefore curriſh, Swine they bee and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſwiniſh. <hi>Oh then I will much and greatly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in the bleſſed Saints and deteſt the curſed doers. For the Lamb and the Doue are two pretty Creatures, but the Dogge and the Hogge are ſullen beaſts.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="91" type="meditation">
               <pb n="146" facs="tcp:12425:80"/>
               <head>91</head>
               <p>THe dainty varieties of pleaſing delights that be among the wicked, draw mens minds with eaſie conſent to vanitie: ſometimes ſhort and ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine delights: ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times long and pleaſant deuiſes are offered, but all be higher points &amp; ſtaires to ſin, oh that man knew the great growing of the ſtinking weed of ſin: virtue growes not without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:12425:80"/> labour, ſin alone &amp; willingly: vertue ſprings after a long ſeaſon, ſinne quickly &amp; in a ſhort ſpace gets vp; yea ſin though but a ſparke ſets all on fire pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently. <hi>I purpoſe then that mine eies ſhalbe watchfull and my heart reſolute, that not the leaſt weed of ſin ſhall grow in me, for I ſee of a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle kernell growes a great tree, of a little ſpawne a great fiſh.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="92" type="meditation">
               <pb n="148" facs="tcp:12425:81"/>
               <head>92</head>
               <p>THe outward duties of Gods ſeruice, I ſee haue long &amp; holily beene obſerued by many: but the inward and hearty du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties I feare mee of a few. Call vpon our formaliſts to practiſe ſome noble deeds of vertue: heereto you ſhall find them ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enclyned. But did they ſerue GOD aright, their minds ſo well trained and long exerciſed in vertue,
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:12425:81"/> would giue ſome rare demonſtration of it. <hi>As for me, I euer wil conceiue, To goe to Church for faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is an abuſe of Religion, and to pray without deuoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is breath to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="93" type="meditation">
               <head>93</head>
               <p>SVch heaps of ſorrows accompany this life as require a vertuous reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of mind to paſſe them ouer: ſometimes heauines of heart aſſailes vs, ſtrange
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:12425:82"/> ſtories ſcarre vs: dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſickneſſe afflicts vs, and wee cannot be quiet, but long to be in our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull country and heauenly dwelling. <hi>Hence this hath bene my reſolute thought. He that will hould out the yeare muſt bide the winter and ſummer, and he that will goe to Heauen must indure the miſeries of this world.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="94" type="meditation">
               <head>94</head>
               <p>IF wee could behold an armed man of an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:12425:82"/> and vnreſiſtable force whoſe violence a thouſand thouſand could not withſtand; it would breed in vs ſome maruai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous contemplations: but greater &amp; extreamer force and violence wee know in ſin, yet we are no whit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed at it: Angells in heauen, men on earth are weake to conquer ſin. But thankes be to Chriſt that hath gotten victory. <hi>But ſince ſins force is ſo violen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>: Ile rufully eye him, but not come nigh him. A ſword hath a ſharp point, and a Cannon a great force,
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:12425:83"/> but let them alone and they will doe no harme.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="95" type="meditation">
               <head>95</head>
               <p>SVch is the foule baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Man, as the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry beaſts out ſtripe him, yea and in many things doe teach him. Some hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites there be artifici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſmoothing vp and ſmothering ſinne which haue not art enough to learne to auoid it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the dumb crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures inſtruct them. Haue
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:12425:83"/> I not ſeene a dog reioyce at the ſight of his Maſter: when his vnchaſt Miſtris will frowne at his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming home? Oh fact full of wretchedneſſe, fuller of diſgrace, and fulleſt of guiltineſſe. <hi>Oh Lord keepe mee that my affections be not drunken with ſuch beaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſinnes, and that I may not be gouerned by them.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="96" type="meditation">
               <head>96</head>
               <p>VVIth vnſpeakeable griefe I haue
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:12425:84"/> thought on the abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble wrongs offred by cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell men to GODS poore Saints, that ſhould haue greateſt kindneſſe: Poore hearts by lofty ſpirits are broken with vnkindneſſe and affliction. Yet com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort comes from aboue, which cheeres their vitall ſpirrits. But oh how theſe throughly wound their conſciences and will God ſuffer theſe wrongs? Oh no, but he will ſhake the ſeat of theſe ſecure Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants. <hi>Me thinkes they are worſe then ſouldiers ſtabd at heart. For hee that is
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:12425:84"/> wounded at hart hath made an end of his daies: but hee that hath a wound in his ſoule knowes not when to end his ſorrow.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="97" type="meditation">
               <head>97</head>
               <p>SVch as were neerely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with ſinne: and haue diſcarded it, know the poyſonful diſpoſition of it: it ſpreads it ſelfe as dead poyſon in a cup, and like a plague infects the ſoundeſt perſons, ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue is not ſo ſpreading,
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:12425:85"/> not ſo ſpeedie in conuey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. <hi>I maruaile not then, why ſo many be bad, and ſo few good. It is becauſe truth hath much a doe to be beleeued, but a lie runnes farre before it be ſtayed.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="98" type="meditation">
               <head>98</head>
               <p>O Full often hath my breaſt ſwollen with eager deſire of heauen, for when I beheld the earth, mine eyes (being my diligent intelligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers) carryes me to much
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:12425:85"/> comfortableneſſe: In this world weepings and mournings, changings, and turnings, vanity and folly euery where a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounds, and he that is in higheſt eſtate euen as a poore wretch with lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing ſteps runs faſt to his graue: But in heauen are all incomparable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies and vneffable dignities. Oh ſweet and noble place to bee in. <hi>Ile be more glad then Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren be of ſweet meat to go to ſuch a country, and to dwell in this neuer enough praiſed City. The vigor of
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:12425:86"/> mens wit, that can ſhew it ſelfe in any ſubiect, muſt here be blunted: they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſpeake enough of this euer-noble City if they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare it with the country, they ſhewe therein moſt rude ſimplicity, if with the Court. Alaſſe a Rich Court is a goodly ſight, but he that lookes vp to Heauen will not care for the world.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="99" type="meditation">
               <head>99</head>
               <p>WHo ſo when they ſee good can loue it, and
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:12425:86"/> affect it. I count ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons my principal friends, whoſe acquaintance I would not ſuperficially entertaine, for ſure there is no ioy in our life if we inioy not ſuch compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, with ſuch I learne holy helpes to heauen, and happy reſolutions, with ſuch I am inſtructed to conquer paſſions, but he that flies from good and ſcoffes at God I count him already with the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell. And though hee walke in the world yet he hath a hell in his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. <hi>This ſhalbe then
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:12425:87"/> mine earneſt intreaty vnto God, that ſuch good and worthy friends which bee this worlds comfort, may not bee drawne away from me by my bad deſert.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="100" type="meditation">
               <head>100</head>
               <p>MEn haue in vſe a two-fould Glaſſe: One moſt for the proud Man, the other for the Wiſe. The proud man whiles hee lookes in his Glaſſe, waxes the prou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: The humble whiles
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:12425:87"/> on his, he waxes the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer. <hi>O Lord grant, while the proud Mans Looking-Glaſse makes him the prou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; my Houre-Glaſſe may make me wiſe to remember my ende.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
